In this module, you will use machine learning to determine if the first stage of Falcon 9 will land successfully. You will split your data into training data and test data to find the best Hyperparameter for SVM, Classification Trees, and Logistic Regression. Then find the method that performs best using test data.

Learning Objectives

Split the data into training testing data
Train different classification models
Optimize the Hyperparameter grid search
Utilize your machine learning skills to build a predictive model to help a business function more efficiently