Predictive Analysis Overview

In this video, we will review Predictive Analysis. In this lab, we will build a machine learning pipeline to predict if the first stage of the Falcon 9 lands successfully. This will include: Preprocessing, allowing us to standardize our data, and Train_test_split, allowing us to split our data into training and testing data, We will train the model and perform Grid Search, allowing us to find the hyperparameters that allow a given algorithm to perform best. Using the best hyperparameter values, we will determine the model with the best accuracy using the training data. You will test Logistic Regression, Support Vector machines, Decision Tree Classifier, and K-nearest neighbors. Finally, we will output the confusion matrix.

