In this module, you will learn about the various libraries in data science. In addition, you will understand an API in relation to REST request and response. Further, in the module, you will explore open data sets on the Data Asset eXchange. Finally, you will learn how to use a machine learning model to solve a problem and navigate the Model Asset eXchange.

Learning Objectives

List the tasks that a data scientist needs to perform to build a model​.
List the various libraries: scientific, visualization, machine learning, and deep learning.
Define REST API in relation to request and response.
Describe data sets and sources of data.
Explore open data sets on the Data Asset eXchange.
Describe how to use a learning model to solve a problem.
Navigate the Model Asset eXchange from IBM Research.