In this module, you will collect data on the Falcon 9 first-stage landings. You will use a RESTful API and web scraping. You will also convert the data into a dataframe and then perform some data wrangling.

Learning Objectives

Create scatter plots and bar charts by writing Python code to analyze data in a Pandas data frame
Write Python code to conduct exploratory data analysis by manipulating data in a Pandas data frame
Create and execute SQL queries to select and sort data
Utilize your data visualization skills to visualize the data and extract meaningful patterns to guide the modeling process