Course Introduction
Hello! And welcome to this capstone course.  

Congratulations for making it this far! My name is Joseph Santarcangelo, Yan Luo and Azim Hirjani . We are pleased to be your instructors and course developers for this capstone course. You will apply your data science skills as a Data scientist for a private space launch company in this project.    

As a starting point of almost all data science projects, you need to collect data, as much and relevant as possible.

You will be collecting data from various sources. After your raw data has been collected, you will need to improve the quality by performing data wrangling. 

Then you can start exploring the processed data.  We will be your guide as we explore some really interesting real-world datasets together. You'll get to practice your SQL skills as we query the data and gather insights.  

You'll gain further insights into the data by applying some basic statistical analysis and data visualization, you'll be able to see directly how variables might be related to each other.   

 We'll drill down into finer levels of detail by splitting the data into groups defined by categorical variables or factors in your data.  

You will be guided to build, evaluate, and refine predictive models for discovering more exciting insights. 

The final task of this capstone project is to create a presentation that will be developed into stories of all your analysis.

Thanks and good luck! 