Data Wrangling Overview

In this video, we will review data wrangling. Let’s review some of the attributes: Flight Number, Date, Booster version, Payload mass Orbit, Launch Site, Outcome: this is the status of the first stage Flights, Grid Fins: these help with landing Reused, Legs: used in landing Landing pad, Block, Reused count, Serial, Longitude and latitude of launch Let’s take a look at some of these attributes. The column “LaunchSite” contains the different launch sites, including: Vandenberg AFB Space Launch Kennedy Space Center CCAFS SLC 40 The column orbits are the different orbits of the payload. For Example: LEO: Low Earth orbit (LEO)is an Earth-centered orbit with an altitude of 2,000 km GTO A geosynchronous orbit is a high Earth orbit that allows satellites to match Earth's rotation. It is located at 22,236 miles (35,786 kilometers) above Earth's equator. The column Outcome indicates if the first stage successfully landed. There are 8 of them, for example. True ASDS means the booster successfully landed to a drone ship as shown the following looped video. False ASDS means the mission outcome was unsuccessfully landed to a drone ship as shown in the video loop. Outcome We would like landing outcomes to be converted to Classes y. y. (either 0 or 1). 0 is a bad outcome, that is, the booster did not land. 1 is a good outcome, that is, the booster did land. The variable Y will represent the classification variable that represents the outcome of each launch.

---
markdown-version: v1
tool-type: theia
branch: lab-5571-instruction
version-history-start-date: '2023-04-12T05:12:06Z'
---
::page{title="Complete the EDA  lab"}

You will need to import and complete the following Jupyter notebook in IBM Watson Studio:

**Right-click the following link, and copy its URL then import it to Watson Studio:**

[EDA ](https://cf-courses-data.s3.us.cloud-object-storage.appdomain.cloud/IBM-DS0321EN-SkillsNetwork/labs/module_1_L3/labs-jupyter-spacex-Data%20wrangling.ipynb)

If you need help with importing notebook to Watson Studio, refer to this lab:

[Import a Notebook into Watson Studio](https://cf-courses-data.s3.us.cloud-object-storage.appdomain.cloud/IBM-DS0321EN-SkillsNetwork/labs/AddingNotebook_toWatson.md.html)

If you see `Failed to Load Notebook` error message, you may go back and check your Notebook list to see if it is a
false alarm that your notebook could be imported already.

