Next Steps

Congratulations on completing this course. We hope you enjoyed it.

As a next step, you can take the appropriate follow-on Python Project from the list below to apply your new found skills in a real-world scenario.

Python Project for Data Science

Python Project for Data Engineering

Python Project for AI & Application Development

Note: Successful completion of this course is a pre-requisite for these Python Project courses. 

You can explore the courses below to further hone and develop your skills for working with Data and Python:

Databases and SQL for Data Science with Python

If you are looking to start a career in Data Science, Data Engineering or AI & Application Development, note that this course is part of the following Professional Certificates which are designed to empower you with the skills to become job-ready in these fields. 

IBM Applied AI Professional Certificate

IBM Data Analyst Professional Certificate

IBM Data Science Professional Certificate

IBM Data Engineering Professional Certificate

IBM Full Stack Cloud Developer Professional Certificate

We encourage you to leave your feedback and rate this course.

Good luck!

