Interactive Visual Analytics and Dashboard

Welcome to the Interactive Visual Analytics and Dashboard module. You will use this to build a Dashboard for stakeholders. Interactive visual analytics enables users to explore and manipulate data in an interactive and real-time way. Common interactions including zoom-in and zoom-out, pan, filter, search, and link. With interactive visual analytics, users could find visual patterns faster and more effectively. Instead of presenting your findings in static graphs, interactive data visualization, or dashboarding, can always tell a more appealing story. In this module, you will be using Folium and Plotly Dash to build an interactive map and dashboard to perform interactive visual analytics. The first part of this module will be focused on analyzing launch site geo and proximities with Folium. We will first mark the launch site locations and their close proximities on an interactive map. Then, we can explore the map with those markers and try to discover any patterns from them. Finally, we should be able to explain how to choose an optimal launch site. Next, you will be building a dashboard application with the Python Plotly Dash package. This dashboard application contains input components such as a dropdown list and a range slider to interact with a pie chart and a scatter point chart. You will be guided to build this dashboard application in an instructional lab. After the dashboard is built, you can use it to find more insights from the SpaceX dataset more easily than with static graphs.

