In this module, you will build a dashboard to analyze launch records interactively with Plotly Dash. You will then build an interactive map to analyze the launch site proximity with Folium.

Learning Objectives

Build an interactive dashboard that contains pie charts and scatter plots to analyze data with the Plotly Dash Python library.
Calculate distances on an interactive map by writing Python code using the Folium library.
Generate interactive maps, plot coordinates, and mark clusters by writing Python code using the Folium library.
Build a dashboard to analyze launch records interactively with Plotly Dash.
Build an interactive map to analyze the launch site proximity with Folium.